A Guide to the Gordon and Webster Family Papers
University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Gordon and Webster Family Papers
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
14573
8500 items, 39 Hollinger boxes, 16 linear feet
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisitions
This collection was a gift to the Albert and Shirley Small Special Collections by Elizabeth Webster, William Webster, Armistead Webster, and Margaret W. McManus on March 12, 2009.
Biographical/Historical Information
Armistead Churchill Gordon, Jr. (1897-1953) was a professor of English Literature at the University of Virginia from 1919 to 1953. He married Cornelia Waddell and they had a daughter Ann Gordon (1929-1994), who became the main connection between the Gordon and Webster families through her marriage to Richard Henry "Harry" Webster (1924-2007). Armistead Churchill Gordon, Jr. was born in Staunton, Virginia to Armistead Churchill Gordon, Sr. (1855-1931) and Maria Breckinridge Catlett Gordon (?-1930). Armistead Churchill Gordon, Sr. was the son of George Loyall Gordon (1829-1862) who died at Malvern Hill during the Civil War and was grandson of the politician, William Fitzhugh Gordon (1787-1858).
Armistead Churchill Gordon, Sr. was an attorney and a writer; graduated from the University of Virginia and William and Mary Law School; practiced law in Staunton, Virginia; was mayor of that city for two years and served as Commonwealth Attorney. He was a member of the Board of Visitors at the University of Virginia for sixteen years; was rector of the University of Virginia (1897-1898; 1906-1918) and was president of the Virginia State Bar Association. In addition to Armistead Churchill Gordon, Jr., he had two other sons, James Lindsay Gordon (1895-1969) and George Loyal l Gordon, (1899-1918) and two daughters, Mary Daniels Gordon, (1893-1980] and Margaret Douglas Gordon [1891-1930's].
Armistead Churchill Gordon, Jr. graduated from William and Mary College and entered military service in World War I at Camp Lee with his younger brother, George Loyall Gordon. Armistead was transferred to the Casual Department and the Gas and War defense. After the war, he received a scholarship to study and teach at the University of Virginia in 1919. He then, married Cornelia Waddell in 1922 and Ann Gordon was born in 1929. After teaching for many years at the University of Virginia, he was called into service during World War II as a Lieutenant General. After several weeks of training at Cambridge, Massachusetts, he was stationed in Washington D. C. Cornelia joined him in an apartment in the city and Ann Gordon was sent to board at St. Anne's Belfield School in Charlottesville, Virginia during the remaining years of the war.
Armistead's brother, James Lindsay Gordon (1895-1969) attended the University of Virginia and served in World War I on the U.S.S. Rijnland that went overseas. He wrote stories when he was younger and had some of them published along with illustrations from his sister, Mary. After the war, James worked full time at the Roanoke Valley and Tie Company in Lexington, North Carolina, and eventually bought the company in 1926. After the depression, he became the City Manager for Lexington, and eventually opened another business, Gordon Veneer Company. He was very outgoing and popular in Lexington. He married Adelaide Thompson Hargrave and they had two daughters, Mary Lindsay Gordon and Adelaide Hargrave Gordon. He wrote letters to his sister, Mary and brother, Armistead but was unable to visit often. Their family stayed in Lexington, North Carolina.
George Loyall Gordon,(1899-1918) named after his grandfather who died at Malvern Hill, attended William and Mary and died of sickness [tetanus] during World War I.
Mary Daniels Gordon was a writer and illustrator, and travelled with her father, Armistead Churchill Gordon, Sr. to New York to meet with publishers about her literary work. Some of her illustrations and stories were published. ("The Chrystal Ball," Little Brown Publishers, and Corks and Curls) She was unmarried and took care of her father until he passed away in 1931. She later moved to Ridgeway Farm in Charlottesville, Virginia, and leased the family house in Staunton.
Armistead's sister, Margaret Douglas Gordon suffered from "nerves" and was admitted to Western State Hospital in Staunton, Virginia in 1917. She later became ill with tuberculosis in 1931, while still at the institution.
Ann Gordon Webster (1929-1994) was the only child of Armistead and Cornelia Gordon. She attended Stonefield School, St. Anne's Belfield School, and Wellesley College. Her husband, Harry Webster (1924-2007) was a graduate of Moses Brown School, Princeton University and attended Harvard Law School. Harry temporarily left Princeton to serve in World War II where he was stationed in Texas, Oklahoma, Hawaii, and Japan. He began his service as a Private and moved up to Corporal and then Sergeant in the medical corps (as an anesthetist, although he had no interest in becoming a doctor). (See Series II: William Webster: Box: 12 Letters to Edward and Alice Blodgett).
Harry and Ann were married in 1949 while she finished her last year of school at Wellesley and he accepted a job in the Foreign Service. He worked for the Central Intelligence Agency and served tours in Madrid; London; Salisbury, Rhodesia; The Hague, and traveled widely in Europe and Latin America. He retired from the Foreign Service in 1973. After retirement Harry continued to travel to his favorite places such as Europe, Costa Rico and his family vacation home in Weld, Maine.
Harry Webster was the son of atomic energy expert, William Webster (1900-1972) and Eleanore Blodgett Webster (?-1961). Eleanore was the daughter of Judge Edward "Peter" Blodgett and Alice Foster Blodgett. William "Bill" or "K" Webster graduated from the Naval Academy in 1920 and the Massachusetts Institute of Technology in 1923. He served in the United States Navy as a Naval Constructor and an officer in the Construction Corps until 1928. He then worked for the New England Electric System in 1928 beginning as an assistant to the general manager and was promoted to vice president in 1942; director in 1950, president in 1959, chief executive officer in 1963, and retired from NEPA in 1970. He was credited with finding peaceful uses for atomic energy, and bringing atomic electric power to New England. He was widely known as the architect of Yankee Atomic Electric Company, and formed ten New England Electric Companies to produce one nuclear power plant.
He also held a number of important government positions, including the chairmanship of the Research and Development Board in the Department of Defense under President Harry S. Truman. One of his charges was to assess the effectiveness of the Hydrogen bomb. He also served in the Office of Scientific Research and Development from 1943 to 1946; was deputy for atomic energy to the Secretary of Defense in 1948; and chairman of the Military Liaison Committee to the Atomic Energy commission in 1951. He was a member and officer of many organizations including the National Advisory Committee for Aeronautics; the Presidents Scientific Advisory Committee; the Army Scientific Advisory Panel; the Massachusetts Institute of Technology; AETNA Life Insurance Company; Federal Reserve Bank of Boston; the Woods Hole Oceanographic Institution; the Huyck Corporation; and chairman of the Rand Corporation. After years of working in the Electric Power industry and serving the government and his country, he received many awards including, the John Fritz Medal of the American Institute of Electrical Engineers. This award recognized him for notable scientific and industrial achievement, specifically leadership in developing peaceful uses of atomic energy. Although he still held many of these titles, he became ill in 1971 and died in 1972.
William Webster was the son of Richard Henry Webster and Harriet Archer Williams. William's mother was the daughter of Stevenson Archer Williams, a well known attorney in Bel Air, Maryland.
William Webster was the son of Richard Henry Webster and Harriet Archer Williams. William's mother was the daughter of Stevenson Archer Williams, a well known attorney in Bel Air, Maryland.
William's mother and father "parted company" in 1920 (but never divorced). His mother was a housemother for Oldfields school in Baltimore, Maryland. His father held a job as a bank teller for a short time, had a tomato canning business, was often broke, and had problems with alcohol. William financially supported both of his parents and several family members.
William Webster had a brother, Stevenson "Steve" Williams Webster (1903-1990), who became the headmaster of several schools including Saint James School. He attended the University of Virginia and developed a friendship with the Gordon family starting in the 1920's. He was very witty, loved to tell stories, and while he was very outgoing, he also enjoyed a quiet life of solitude and love of nature. He was responsible for introducing Harry Webster to Ann Gordon.
In addition to his brother, William also had two sisters, Anna ("Nan") Stump Webster Wolff and Ariel Hope ("Hope") Harlan. Hope and her husband Herbert Harlan had one daughter, Hope who married William Dallam. They had four children, Katie, William, Ariel, and David. Nan and her husband Miles Wolff (writer and Managing Editor of The Evening Sun and Executive Director of the Greensboro Daily News) had two daughters, Eliza ("Lila") McCormick Wolff, Anna Wolff Dixon, Jr. and one son, Miles ("Bee") Hoffman Wolff, Jr.
In 1961, William Webster's wife, ("Roo") was tragically killed in an automobile crash while on a trip with him in North Carolina. The car accident resulted in a lawsuit against the Webster estate and William settled out of court the following year. Also in 1961 Harry Webster ("Tig") was assigned to Salisbury, Rhodesia. Harry left for his assignment, and Ann Gordon and the children stayed with William in Washington, D.C. to help him recover from his injuries and the devastating loss of his wife. In 1963, William married his secretary, Miss Vollie Sanderson, who worked for the New England Power Association and had handled the business and affairs of the Webster family for many years. The Webster family used nicknames from Winnie the Pooh characters, William was referred to as "K" for Kanga, Eleanore as "Roo," and Harry, as "Tigger" or "Tig."Harry and Ann Gordon Webster had four children, William ("Barney") Webster (1951-present,) Elizabeth ("Liza") Webster (1955-present,) Armistead ("Oppit") Webster (1957-present,) and Margaret ("Maggie") Webster (1959-present) and seven grandchildren including Kiely Webster, Stevenson Webster, Ariel Webster, Daniel Ladd, Sarah Ladd, Ellie McManus, and Rob McManus.
Harry and Ann Gordon Webster had four children, William ("Barney") Webster (1951-present,) Elizabeth ("Liza") Webster (1955-present,) Armistead ("Oppit") Webster (1957-present,) and Margaret ("Maggie") Webster (1959-present) and seven grandchildren including Kiely Webster, Stevenson Webster, Ariel Webster, Daniel Ladd, Sarah Ladd, Ellie McManus, and Rob McManus.
Scope and Content
This collection is mostly family correspondence that documents the lives of the Gordon and Webster family members. Of particular interest are William "Bill" Webster (1900-1972), his son Richard Henry "Harry" Webster, (1924-2007) and Armistead Churchill Gordon, Jr. (1897-1953). The Webster and Gordon families were connected through the marriage of Harry Webster and Ann Gordon (1929-1994) in 1949. Ann Gordon's father, Armistead Churchill Gordon, Jr. (1897-1953) taught English Literature at the University of Virginia from 1919 to 1953 and was from Staunton, Virginia. There are also some letters from Ann Gordon's grandfather, Armistead Churchill Gordon, Sr. (1855-1931) who was a successful attorney, writer, and rector of the University of Virginia in 1897-1898 and in 1906-1918 (in Series I Armistead Churchill Gordon, Jr. Boxes: 2- 9). Harry Webster's father, William Webster was president of the New England Power Company and chairman of the Research and Development Board for the Department of Defense (studying atomic power) under President Harry S. Truman. Harry Webster worked in the Foreign Service from the 1950's through to the 1970's with tours in Madrid, Spain; Salisbury, Rhodesia; London, England; The Hague, Holland; and secretly [Dominican Republic 1965-1966]
Although the collection is mostly personal family letters, topics of interest are the University of Virginia; Charlottesville, Virginia; English literature; the Atomic Energy Commission; the National Security Council; the United States Information Services; the Central Intelligence Agency; and the United States Navy. The collection is grouped into five series, Armistead Churchill Gordon, Jr.; William Webster; Ann Gordon Webster; Webster family (Harry and Ann, and their children); and printed material. It consists of approximately 8,600 items, 41 Hollinger boxes, and 17 linear feet.
There are original manuscripts (poems and stories) by Armistead Churchill Gordon, Jr. and family members. (Series I: Armistead Churchill Gordon, Jr.: Manuscripts: Box: 1) Armistead's sister, Mary Daniels Gordon (1893-1980), was a writer and illustrator of children's books. It is mentioned that she did some illustrations for the University of Virginia Corks and Curls and had at least one book published, ("The Chrystal Ball" by Brown & Little Co.) (Series I: Armistead Churchill Gordon: Gordon family correspondence Boxes: 3-7)
There is correspondence concerning the publication of Armistead Churchill Gordon, Jr.'s dissertation in 1923, "Fugitive Verses of Virginia Writers." (Series I: Armistead Churchill Gordon, Jr.: General correspondence Box: 2)
The collection also has correspondence that mentions University of Virginia faculty and members of the Charlottesville community, including Atcheson and Virginia Hench, Carl and Margaret Speidel, William and Elizabeth Weedon, George and Virginia Zehmer, Frank and Jeanette Geldard, James and Betty Kindred; William Cabell Bruce, Phillip Bruce, Philippa Bruce, Art Shepperson, John Luck, Edward Younger, Dr. Paul and Anna Barringer, and Colgate Darden. The correspondence mostly mentions daily activities of the faculty and their families such as travel, general health, bridge, tennis, and social engagements. (Series I: Armistead Churchill Gordon: Gordon family correspondence Boxes: 3-7; and Series III: Ann Gordon Webster: family correspondence Boxes: 13-17).
Included in the general correspondence are letters from John Cooke Wyllie and James Southall Wilson. There are letters from and about John Armstrong Chaloner, a famous and eccentric member of the Astor family of New York, who lived at Merrie Mills, Cobham, Virginia and was a friend of the Gordon family. (Series: 1 Armistead Churchill Gordon: general correspondence: Box: 2 and Gordon family correspondence Boxes: 3-7)
The family correspondence is from 1914 to 1931 and includes Armistead Gordon, Jr. and his siblings, James Lindsay Gordon, George Loyall Gordon, Mary Daniels Gordon, Margaret Douglas Gordon, and their parents, Armistead Churchill Gordon, Sr., and Maria ("Ria") Breckinridge Catlett Gordon of Staunton, Virginia. The letters describe college life at William and Mary and the University of Virginia in 1917 as well as military service during World War I. (Series I: Armistead Churchill Gordon: Gordon family correspondence Boxes: 4-8) Armistead's youngest brother, George Loyall Gordon died from an illness (tetanus from contact with a rusty nail?) during the war. In 1918 Armistead's sister, Margaret Gordon, was sent to Western State Hospital in Staunton, Virginia where Dr. Joseph DeJarnette diagnosed her with tuberculosis in 1931. There is very little mention of Margaret but there is a letter in which she wrote to her father pleading with him to let her return home. Her later letters seem to suggest that she didn't mind staying there and that the hospital was a nice retreat and the people were very pleasant. (Series I: Armistead Churchill Gordon, Jr. Gordon family correspondence: Box: 5)
There are minutes of the Board of Visitors from 1931 to 1936 with notes by Armistead Churchill Gordon, Sr. and a dedication to James Southall Wilson and Wilson Hall by Fredson Bowers. (Series I: Armistead Churchill Gordon, Jr.: University of Virginia Box: 9) There is also a proposal to move the medical school to Richmond, Virginia (Series I: Armistead Churchill Gordon: Gordon family correspondence Box: 6)
There is early correspondence of the Webster family in which Harry Webster wrote letters to his grandparents, Peter and Alice Blodgett describing his daily life in the service in World War II in Texas, Oklahoma, Hawaii, and Japan. (Series II William Webster: Box: 12).
The correspondence of William and Harry Webster includes letters from government officials such as Robert Ellison; William T. Golden; Robert Cutler; William Spraque; David E. Lilienthal,Chairman U. S. Atomic Energy Commission; James Forrestal, Secretary of Defense; J. E. Hull, Lieutenant General, Office of the Secretary of Defense; Art Davis, Rear Admiral United States Navy, Director, Joint Chiefs of Staff; George F. Kennan, The Counselor, Department of State; and Presidents Richard M. Nixon, Dwight D. Eisenhower, and Harry S. Truman. J. Robert Oppenheimer is mentioned by name but no detailed information about him is included in the collection.
There are reports from the Research and Development Board of the United States Defense Department which was sometimes referred to as the "Gaither's Committee." There are secret reports regarding the Atomic Energy Commission and National Security Council (Series II: William Webster Box: 10)
There is also genealogical information about both the Gordon and Webster families, including a will for James Lindsay in 1782 in which he specified the sale of his slaves. (Series I: Armistead Churchill Gordon: Genealogy: Coleman) In the Webster family, there is genealogical information about William Webster's grandfather, Stevenson Archer Williams, a successful attorney in Bel Air, Maryland from 1851-1932. (Series II: William Webster: Box: 12)
There is also a court transcript of a lawsuit against William Webster in which his wife, Eleanore Blodgett Webster was the driver in a car accident that killed her and several individuals from another car. (Series II: William Webster: Box: 12)
There are miscellaneous news clippings about Theodore Roosevelt, American politics, and the CIA in Series IV Webster family (Harry and Ann) Box: 37.
The Webster family letters include letters from William Webster and his son, Harry Webster, as well as letters from other close family members such as William's brother Stevenson Williams Webster. The letters between William Webster and Harry Webster reveal only vague sketches of their work such as names of conferences, travel dates, court hearings, government officials, and colleagues, but they do allude to important people and events. There are letters from Ann Webster to Harry Webster referring to the danger in Santo Domingo in 1965.
The collection also includes information and correspondence with Harry and Ann Gordon Webster 's four children, William ("Barney") Webster, Elizabeth ("Liza") Webster, Armistead ("Oppit") Webster, and Margaret ("Maggie") Webster McManus and their children (Harry and Ann's grandchildren). There are also letters from various uncles, aunts, cousins, nieces and nephews of the Webster and Gordon families.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into five series: Series I Armistead Gordon, Jr.; Series II William Webster; Series III Ann Gordon Webster; Series IV The Webster family (Ann and Harry Webster and their children); and, Series V Printed material from both families.The folders are arranged alphabetically by subject categories and the letters are arranged chronologically within each folder.
Box and Contents List
- Series I: Armistead Churchill Gordon, Jr.
  - Subseries A. Manuscripts (Box-folder 1:1-16)
    - n. d. Manuscript Biography of H.A. Jones, 3 items (Box-folder 1:1)
      There is a typewritten biography of Jones and a news clipping. There is also a typewritten essay on Henrik Ibsen.
    - 1917Manuscript by Margaret Douglas Gordon, 1 item (Box-folder 1:2)
      "Delhi Dominoes"
    - n. d. Manuscript by Mary Gordon, 1 item (Box-folder 1:3)
      "The Fish that Got Away"
    - n. d. Manuscripts by the members of the Gordon family, 14 items (Box-folder 1:4)
      There are various unpublished hand written and typed manuscripts by A.C. Gordon, Sr.; A.C. Gordon, Jr.; and sisters Mary and Margaret Gordon.
    - 1879-1898n. d. Manuscripts by the members of the Gordon family, 18 items (Box-folder 1:5)
      There are various unpublished manuscripts.
    - n. d. Manuscripts by the members of the Gordon family, 24 items (Box-folder 1:6)
    - n. d. Manuscripts by the members of the Gordon family, 7 items (Box-folder 1:7)
      There are various unpublished manuscripts
    - n. d. Manuscript by James Nelson Waddell, 1 item (Box-folder 1:8)
    - n. d. Manuscript notes for an autobiography of Armistead Churchill Gordon, Sr., 1 item (Box-folder 1:9)
    - n. d. Unknown manuscript, 1 item (Box-folder 1:10)
      There is a story in typescript about poker.
    - n. d. Miscellaneous book inventory of Gordon's library, 1 item (Box-folder 1:11)
    - 1917-1918 Notebook for class about Shakespeare, 1 item (Box-folder 1:12)
    - n. d. Notes, 1 item (Box-folder 1:13)
    - n. d. Miscellaneous class notes, 4 items (Box-folder 1:14)
      There is a class roster and notes on modern British drama, English 104, an essay on Poe by [a student] and an essay about teaching and the use of textbooks.
    - n. d. Poem notebook, 1 item (Box-folder Folder: 15)
    - 1886-1891 Poems by James Nelson Waddell, 18 items (Box-folder 1:16)
      James Waddell was Armistead Gordon's father-in-law
  - Subseries B. General Correspondence (Box-folder 2:1-11:6)
    - 1917-1946 [1881] General correspondence of Armistead Churchill Gordon, Jr., 41 items (Box-folder 2:1)
      Earnest J. Oglesby congratulated Armistead on receiving the Cary Scholarship. Theodore P. Campbell wrote about a vacancy in the English Department at Virginia Tech paying twelve hundred dollars per year. There are also letters about renting the Gordon home. Some of the correspondents include H. A. Watt; Charles Gordon; Frances Courtenay Baylor; J. Leslie Hall; card signed by Nell Battle Lewis; Frank Dodd; Sallie Baylor Landrum; Rosewell Page; Captain A. G. Pape; Robert M. Hughes; George Fawcett; James P. C. Southall; J. William McCutchan; Charlie Doughtie; Patricia E. Best; Stan R. Durkee; G. Ray Thompson; Stevenson Williams Webster; Ruth Ford; Florence Leutz; Pleas Conquest; R. E. Higginbotham; Charlie Darling; John F. Latimer; Francis Coleman Rosenberger; Steve Webster, and Mrs. J. Austin (Mary Blackburn) Devine
    - 1947-1952 General correspondence of Armistead Churchill Gordon, Jr., 39 items (Box-folder 2:2)
      There are letters from friends, students, and colleagues from the military and letters from Armistead Gordon regarding Ann's wedding. Correspondents include Mrs. J. Austin Devine; Reymond Cochrane; Letha and Claude Solterbeck; G. R. Thompson; Sherman L. Whipple; [W. P. C.;] Mrs. R. H. B. Wade; Jerry Burrows, Stan R. Durkee; Pam Morten; and Don Lewis
    - 19331943 General correspondence Armistead Churchill Gordon and John Cook Wyllie, 3 items (Box-folder 2:3)